Guide to the Gilbert-Cheever Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gilbert-Cheever family papers
1836-1891
MS 700
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(16 boxes)
The papers document the families formed by the marriages of two sisters, Mary and Fanny Goodridge, to William Hinman Gilbert and Henry A. Cheever, respectively. William H. Gilbert was a clergyman from Weston, Connecticut who, with his wife, taught in schools in Vermont and Massachusetts. Henry A. Cheever was a sea captain who settled in San Francisco ca. 1853 and brought his wife and children there from Massachusetts. The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, journals, record books, photographs, memorabilia, printed matter, and sermons relating to the lives of these two families and their children.The Cheever letters from San Francisco describe the political and social life of the city in addition to carrying news of the family and domestic activities. William E. Goodridge, brother of the two Goodridge sisters, wrote from the West where he described life in Nevada. After his death in 1864, his fiancee Sara A. Gonsalves continued to write to the family from Washington D.C. with descriptions of visits to soldiers' hospitals and other references to the Civil War. William H. Gilbert, who was an army agent of the American Bible Society (1864-1865), also reported on the Civil War and later, writing on his travels in Alabama in 1870, described the lynching of a black school teacher.
Gilbert family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederic B. Schell, Jr., and Alice Horrax Schell in 1973 and 1976.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Diaries, Journals, Memorandum Books, and Account Books. III. Memorabilia, Printed Matter, and Photographs. IV. Sermons of W. H. Gilbert.
Scope and Contents
The Gilbert-Cheever Family Papers contain correspondence, diaries, journals, record books, documents, photographs, memorabilia, printed matter, and sermons relating to members of the Goodridge, Gilbert and Cheever families from about 1836 to 1900, with the bulk of the material from 1840 to 1880. Much of the materials in the papers is of a personal and family nature, describing details of domestic and social life in New England and San Francisco during the period. Subjects include diet, medicine(particularly diabetes), and death; education, primarily at Yale College, Bradford Academy (Massachusetts), and other schools; and religion, both attitudes of individuals and activities of religious organizations. There is also material concerning the shipping trade and life at sea during the 1840's and early 1850's; life in San Francisco from about 1853 to the 1880's; and the Civil War.
Also included is a significant amount of material concerning William Hinman Gilbert's pastorships in several New England towns from 1844 to 1864; his work for the American Bible Society and the U.S. Christian Commission, primarily from 1864 to 1882; and his real estate investments in Virginia during 1890-1891.
The papers are arranged in four series:
I. CORRESPONDENCE
II. DIARIES, JOURNALS, MEMORANDUM BOOKS AND ACCOUNT BOOKS
III. MEMORABILIA, PRINTED MATTER AND PHOTOGRAPHS
IV. SERMONS OF WILLIAM HINMAN GILBERT
CORRESPONDENCE consists chiefly of letters between family members and friends, and also includes some of Reverend William Hinman Gilbert's correspondence and reports regarding his work for religious organizations from 1864 to 1880.
A large part of the correspondence consists of letters to Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert from friends and family members, particularly her sister Fanny (Goodridge) Cheever and her husband Henry A. Cheever. During the 1840's and early 1850's, Henry A. Cheever often wrote to his wife and sister-in-law from ports such as Havana and New Orleans. After the Cheevers settled in San Francisco about 1853, they (particularly Fanny) maintained a steady correspondence with their friends and relatives back in "the States," extolling the climate and scenery of California, but decrying the violence, greed and corruption they saw in California life. As one commented in a letter to a New England relative, "One year's experience in California is equal to five in Massachusetts." Fanny's frequent letters to her sister Mary and to other relatives provide a continuing account of family illnesses, accidents, finances, visitors, livestock, gardens and other domestic activities, as well as observations on high prices, hard times, elections and other events in San Francisco.
William E. Goodridge's letters to his New England relatives are curiously vague as to the nature of his work; in one letter he commented that his family might not understand or approve of what he was doing. Apparently he did travel frequently, worked for a time for the express company, and was involved in a political campaign in Nevada. In his letters he wrote of his impressions and his feelings about the West, suggesting rather than describing in detail his experiences. In 1864 he described the rapid transformation of Nevada from a "savage wilderness" to a civilized society. From her homes in New York, eastern Pennsylvannia, and then Washington, D.C., William's fiancée, Sara A. Gonsalves, wrote to Mrs. Gilbert concerning her hopes that William could return to the East. Following his death in October 1864, Sara described her tremendous grief. Her letters, dated 1861-1865, also commented on the effects of the Civil War, including descriptions of visits to soldiers' hospitals, a threatened invasion of Pennsylvania in 1862, visits to Congress, news reports of battles, celebrations of the capture of Vicksburg, and the New York draft riots. Sara's father, M.J. Gonsalves, wrote to Mrs. Gilbert in May 1865, describing his work as army chaplain at a hospital in Louisiana and the grief of former slaves over President Lincoln's assassination.
Another valuable perspective on the Civil War is provided by Reverend Gilbert's reports and correspondence concerning his work as a delegate of the U.S. Christian Commission and an army agent of the American Bible Society in 1864 and 1865. Of particular interest are his comments on conditions in Richmond in April 1865 and his reports of an expedition in May 1865 to recover bodies hastily buried at the Cold Harbor battlefield. Many of Gilbert's reports were copied in a letterpress book, dated February - July 1865.
Correspondence concerning Reverend Gilbert's career as a Congregational minister and as a Bible Society agent is scattered throughout the series. An interesting letter to Reverend Gilbert from Alabama in July 1870 vividly describes the lynching of a black teacher, including a copy of his last letter to his wife in Canada. Newspaper clippings describe the incident from a much different perspective. Correspondence for 1890 and 1891 includes information concerning Gilbert's interest in land investment in Virginia.
The series also contain letters written by Charles Minor Gilbert and George Edwards Gilbert while students at Yale and later while teaching school. The twin brothers exchanged frequent letters with each other, with their two sisters, and with their parents, concerning student life at Yale, their teaching positions, their illnesses with diabetes, and family news and visits. Letters exchanged with several doctors discuss diets, medication, and treatment for diabetes. There are also two letters from Professor Thomas A. Thacher of Yale to Reverend William H. Gilbert: May 25, 1872, offering financial assistance to enable Gilbert to send his two sons to Yale, despite the high cost; and February 7, 1880, regarding repayment of a loan for his sons' education.
Most of the material in the DIARIES, JOURNALS, MEMORANDUM BOOKS AND ACCOUNT BOOKS series consists of the journals, memorandum books and other record books kept by William Hinman Gilbert from 1847 to 1899. These volumes provide an unusually full and detailed account of his activities and observations. His journals from 1864 to 1865 are particularly interesting. The series also contains a diary kept by Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert of her trip to San Francisco in 1878, and notebooks and diaries of Charles Minor Gilbert and George. Edwards Gilbert.
MEMORABILIA, PRINTED MATTER AND PHOTOGRAPHS contains biographical and genealogical information, printed matter, photographs, printed sermons, documents, essays, notes and memorabilia such as programs, invitations, pins and autograph books, relating to William Hinman Gilbert, Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert, Charles Minor Gilbert and George Edwards Gilbert. Of interest are publications, printed sermons, and documents relating to Reverend Gilbert's pastorships and to his work with religious organizations. Also included are Yale College memorabilia, photographs, and student essays and notes belonging to Reverend Gilbert and his sons Charles and George. Yale College catalogues, class record books, and a Class of 1878 photograph album have been transferred to the Yale College publications collection.
Series IV, SERMONS OF WILLIAM HINMAN GILBERT, consists of an extensive file of Reverend Gilbert's sermon manuscripts from 1844 to 1864. His early sermons (1844-1854) were numbered in chronological sequence; most of these sermons and many later sermons contain notations of dates and places where each sermon was preached. Some sermons were delivered ten or more times and a number were re-written at later dates. Numbered sermons marked as re-written have been arranged by the date of the revision rather than in Gilbert's numerical sequence. Undated sermons, sermon outlines, and notes are arranged in order of the biblical text on which the sermon was based. The series also contains sermon plans, 1844-1845 and n.d., which consist of notes on various biblical texts, topics to be covered and commentary for sermons. These were apparently compiled from courses taken at Yale Divinity School.
The papers were given to the Yale University Library in 1973 by Frederic B. Schell, Jr., and Alice (Horrax) Schell. Additional papers, including correspondence, memorabilia, and sermons, were given in 1976. Arrangement of the papers was completed in July 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Gilbert-Cheever Family Papers relate to members of the Goodridge, Gilbert and Cheever families of New England and California from about 1836 to 1900. The papers primarily concern the Reverend William Hinman Gilbert (1817-1905); his second wife Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert (1823-1895) their four children George Edwards Gilbert (1855-1879), Charles Minor Gilbert (1855-1881), Annie Ward Gilbert (1857-?); and Mary Alice Gilbert(1860-?); and Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert Is sister Fanny (Goodridge) Cheever (1825-?) and her husband Henry. A. Cheever (?-1873).
William Hinman Gilbert was born in 1817 in Weston, Connecticut, the son of Ezra and Rebecca (Minor) Gilbert. He graduated from Yale College in 1841, continued his studies at the Andover Theological Seminary from 1842 to 1843, and graduated from the Yale Divinity School in 1845. From 1845 to 1846 he was the minister at Haddam, Connecticut, where he married Elizabeth Mosely of Westfield, Massachusetts, on December 29, 1845. In March 1846 they moved to Westminster, Vermont, where he was pastor of the Congregational Church until 1851. Elizabeth (Mosely) Gilbert died in December 1846 in Westminster, leaving a son, William ("Willie") P.M. Gilbert, who married Jessie A. Little in 1870; they settled in Oberlin, Ohio where Willie worked as an assistant postmaster. They had five children: May Elizabeth (born March 1871, died September 1871); Edward Ellis (born June 1873); Winnie Emeline (born October 1875); William Henry (born October 1877); and a third son (born January 1880).
On April 10, 1849, Reverend Gilbert married Mary Goodridge, daughter of Joseph and Roxanna (Edwards) Goodridge of Westminster, Vermont, who was a graduate of and teacher at Bradford Academy in Massachusetts. She is an important figure in the papers, connecting the Goodridge, Gilbert and Cheever families; much of the correspondence in the papers is addressed to her.
Mary's sister, Fanny Goodridge, married Henry A. Cheever, a sea captain in the shipping trade during the 1840's and early 1850's. During a voyage to California he decided to stay in San Francisco and persuaded his wife Fanny and their children to move there from Massachusetts. He was employed in shipping, mining and real estate in California, and became active in San Francisco politics. Two of Mary's brothers, William E. Goodridge and Joseph Goodridge, also moved to California. William stayed with the Cheevers for a time, then moved on to other places in the West, eventually working his way to the Nevada territory where he died in October 1864.
Reverend Gilbert and his wife Mary remained in New England in spite of Henry A. Cheever's attempts to lure them to California. Reverend Gilbert was pastor of the Congregational Church in Ashfield, Massachusetts, from 1851 to 1855, where his twin sons Charles Minor and George Edwards were born on April 22, 1855. From 1855 to 1864, he was pastor of the Congregational Church in Granby, Connecticut, where his daughters Annie Ward and Mary Alice were born June 30,1857, and April 23, 1860, respectively. In 1864, Reverend Gilbert was appointed Superintendent of Scripture Distribution in the U.S. Army by the American Bible Society and the U.S. Christian Commission, with headquarters in Washington, D.C., and Baltimore. During 1864 and 1865 he travelled to army encampments and towns, primarily in Virginia and Maryland, overseeing the distribution of Bibles among the soldiers and visiting hospitals and prisons.
From the fall of 1865 until 1869, Reverend Gilbert was an agent for the Vermont Bible Society, and in 1868 both he and his wife served as principals of the Classical and English Boarding School in Norwich, Vermont. From 1870 to 1871 he was Superintendent of the American Bible Society for Connecticut and Western Massachusetts; from 1871 to 1878 he was Superintendent of the American Bible Society in New England; and from 1878 to 1900 he was Secretary of the Connecticut Bible Society. In the fall of 1900 he moved to California, where he died in 1905.
Charles Miner Gilbert and George Edwards Gilbert both entered Yale College in 1874 and graduated in 1878. After graduating from Yale, George Edwards taught school in Englewood, New Jersey, until his death from diabetes in September 1879. Charles Minor also taught school, in Peekskill, N.Y., and in New York City; he died in April 1881, also from diabetes. Annie Gilbert later became Mrs. Hobson, and Mary Alice married Edwin Horrax in 1886. Mary Alice and Edwin Horrax had three children, Gilbert, William and Alice. Gilbert Horrax, who married Geraldine Martin, became a doctor and was associated with the surgeon Harvey Williams Cushing. Alice Horrax married Frederic B. Schell, Jr., in 1922.
African Americans; Brothers and sisters; Congregational churches; Death; Diabetes; Diet; Families; Lynching; Shipping; Nevada -- Description and travel; New England -- Social life and customs; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Social life and customs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia -- Economic conditions; West (U.S.); Account books; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Shipmasters; Women teachers; Cheever, Fanny Goodridge, b. 1825; Cheever, Henry A., d. 1873; Gilbert, Annie Ward, b. 1857; Gilbert, Charles Minor, 1855-1881; Gilbert, George Edwards, 1855-1879; Gilbert, Mary Alice, b. 1860; Gilbert, Mary Goodridge, 1823-1895; Gilbert, William H. (William Hinman), 1817-1905; Gonsalves, M. J.; Gonsalves, Sara A.; Goodridge, Joseph; Goodridge, William E., d. 1864; Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1815-1886; Cheever family; Gilbert family; American Bible Society; Bradford Junior College (Bradford, Mass.); United States Christian Commission; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1841; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1878; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Divinity School
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1836-(1851-1883)1891; Series I; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged chronologically, with a few folders of undated letters filed at the end of the series.
  The number of items are contained in parentheses these are represented at the end of the unitdate
  - 1836 (1) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1839 (2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1840-1842 (1) (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - 1842 (1) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1843 (10) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1844 (12) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1845 (13) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1846 (28) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1847 (11) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1848 (6) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1849 (8) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [1840-1949?] (3) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1850 (5) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1851 (17) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1852 January-June (20) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1852 July-December (20) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1853 (20) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1854 January-April (18) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1854 May-Dec, undated (21) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1855 (20) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1856 (19) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1857 (19) (Box 2, Folder 22a)
  - 1858 (16) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1859 (9) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1860 (4) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1861 (6) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1862 (8) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1863 (6) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1864 (15) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 1865 (7) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Record book of letters and reports written by William Hinman Gilbert (carbon copies) (1) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - William Hinman Gilbert: letters and 1865 reports relating to the U.S. Christian Commission and American Bible Society (10) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1866 (4) (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 1867 (7) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 1868 (2) (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 1869 (26) (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - 1870 January-June (13) (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - 1870 July-December (17) (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - 1871 (28) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - 1872 (22) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - 1873 (8) (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - 1874 January-June (15) (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - 1874 July-December (27) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - 1875 (33) (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - 1876 January-June (26) (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - 1876 July-December (25) (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - 1877 (27) (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - 1878 January-June (16) (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - 1878 July-August (22) (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - 1878 September (36) (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - 1878 October (54) (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - 1878 November (47) (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - 1878 December and undated (46) (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - 1879 January 1-15 (37) (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - 1979 January 16-31 (30) (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - 1879 February (27) (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - 1879 March (37) (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - 1879 April (21) (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - 1879 May (25) (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - 1879 June-August (23) (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - 1879 September (22) (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - 1879 October (32) (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - 1879 November (18) (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - 1879 December (21) (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - 1880 January-February (32) (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - 1880 March (22) (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - 1880 April-May (31) (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - 1880 June-August (32) (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - 1880 September-December (38) (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - 1881 January-April (25) (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - 1881 May-December (13) (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - 1882 (15) (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - 1883 (11) (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - 1884, 1886 (12) (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - 1890 (5) (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - 1891 (11) (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Undated - located among letters from circa 1840-1860 (16) (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Undated - located among letters from circa 1850-1870 (14) (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Undated - located among letters from circa 1852-1855 (22) (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Undated - located among letters almost exclusively from years 1877-1882 (18) (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Undated (9) (Box 5, Folder 81)
- DIARIES, JOURNALS, MEMORANDUM BOOKS AND ACCOUNT BOOKS, 1847-1899; Series II; 2 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains material belonging to the following family members:
  William Hinman Gilbert
  Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert
  Charles Minor Gilbert
  George Edwards Gilbert
  The papers are arranged chronologically under the names of each of the above family members.
  The number of items are contained in parentheses before the unitdate
  - William Hinman Gilbert
    - Parish and preaching record books (3), 1847-1855 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Record of a bee colony (1), 1856 February-1857 November 7 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Journals (3), 1852-1854, 1856-1858, 1859 January 1-November 30, 1859 December 3-December 20, 1860 January 1-November 12 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Journals (2), 1861-1862, 1863 January 1-December 31, 1864 January 1-September 26 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Journal (1), 1864 October 1-1865 May 21 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Appointment and expense book (1), 1865-1866 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Journal (1), 1865 June 12-October 28, 1865 November 4-1866 July 13 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
    - Journal (1), 1866 July 14-1868 March 8 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Account book (1), 1866-1868 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (3), 1868 October 14-1869 June 1, 1869 June 1-August 31, 1869 September 1-November 7 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (4), 1869 November 9-1870 January 20, 1870 January 21 March 25, 1870 March 26 May 31, 1870 June 1-June 28 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (3), 1870 September 1-1875 (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
    - Account book (1), 1875 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (3), 1876 January 1-December 31, 1877 January 1-December 31, 1878 January 1-December 31 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (3), 1879-1884 July 22, 1885-1886 April 11 (Box 8, Folder 19-21)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (2), 1886 April 12-1889 June 24 (Box 8, Folder 22-23)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (4), 1889 July 1-October 2, 1889 October 2-December 20, 1889 December 22-1890 March 12, 1890 March 1-September 13 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (3), 1890 September 14-November 24, 1890 November 25-1891 February 18, 1891 February 19-May 15 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Memorandum books (include journal) (2), 1891 May 16-December 22, 1891 December 23 1892 August 23 and 1893 March 23-24, 1892 July 26-1893 July 4 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Memorandum books (include journal)(2), 1893 July 4- 1899 March 1 (Box 9, Folder 28-31)
  - Mary (Goodridge) Gilbert
    - Diary of a visit to San Francisco, 1878 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Charles Minor Gilbert
    - Diary (1), 1873 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Notebooks (2), 1876, 1879-1880 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - George Edwards Gilbert
    - Diaries, 1873, 1874 (Box 9, Folder 35)
- MEMORABILIA, PRINTED MATTER AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1790, 1840-1882; Series III; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  The papers in this series relate to the following:
  The papers are arranged under the names of the above individuals.
  - William Hinman Gilbert
    - Biographical information; photograph (8), 1873, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Emblems of K.E.E., Yale chapter (2), 1840 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous papers related to theological studies at Andover Theological Seminary and Yale Divinity School, Circa 1842-1851 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Davis, Reverend Emerson, Memoir of Mrs. Elizabeth Gilbert, Westfield, Massachusetts: H.B. Smith (Mrs. W.H. Gilbert, 1821-1846) (1), 1849 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Sermon delivered at the [Congregational] Church in Westminster, Vermont (1), 1790 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous papers related to the First Congregational Church. of Westminster, Vermont (4), 1851 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers related to the Congregational Church in Ashfield, Massachusetts (9), Circa 1851-1855 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous papers related to the Congregational Church of Granby, Connecticut (12), 1856-1864 (Box 10, Folder 8)